Guide to the Frederick C. Crawford Films, 1936-1980 RL.10007
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Frederick C. Crawford films
1936-1980
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Crawford, Frederick Coolidge
RL.10007
6 Linear Feet
The Frederick C. Crawford films consist of 38 16mm films chronicling the travels of Cleveland businessman Frederick C. Crawford from 1936 to 1980. In addition, the collection includes a photo album presented to Crawford by Trans World Airlines in 1953, documenting an around-the-world survey, in which Crawford participated as a technical consultant, that TWA completed in 1952.
Biographical Note
Frederick Coolidge Crawford was born in Watertown, Massachusetts in 1891. He graduated from Harvard University with an A.B. in 1913, and in 1914 with a master's degree in civil engineering. On Nov. 4, 1916, Crawford was hired as a millwright helper by auto and airplane parts manufacturer Steel Products in Cleveland, Ohio, which became Thompson Products in 1926. In 1933 Crawford became president of the company, a position he held for 25 years. He would serve the company in other capacities until 1985. Noted for his business acumen and skill as a communicator, Crawford was also a noted philanthropist and fundraiser. He served in numerous business, civic, educational, honorary and professional organizations, raising millions of dollars for health, welfare and education. Frederick C. Crawford died in 1994.
Related Materials
Frederick C. Crawford Family Papers (Western Reserve Historical Society)
Provenance
The Frederick C. Crawford films were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2012.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Original audiovisual materials may require production of listening or viewing copies before use.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Collection Overview
The Frederick C. Crawford films consist of 38 16mm films chronicling the travels of Cleveland businessman Frederick C. Crawford from 1936 to 1980. In addition, the collection includes a photo album presented to Crawford by Trans World Airlines in 1953, documenting an around-the-world survey, in which Crawford participated as a technical consultant, that TWA completed in 1952. The collection has two primary areas of focus, with 12 of the films coming from trips Crawford took to his vacation home in Cat Cay, Bahamas, and 19 of the films produced from a safari Crawford, along with Gordon and Vernon Stouffer, sponsored in 1955, which resulted in the collection of a number of specimens for the Cleveland Zoo. Other Crawford travel represented in the collection includes trips to Europe in 1936 and 1939, a trip around the world in 1959, a cruise from Cleveland to Fiji in 1958, a trip to Russia in 1959, a trip to the Middle East and Greece in 1961, and trips to his other homes in Vermont and Massachusetts. This collection is part of the Archive of Documentary Arts. The original films are closed to research access pending reformatting.
Organization of the Collection
This collection is organized into two series, Films and Related Materials.
Jerusalem; Kenya; Sri Lanka; 16mm; Cotuit (Mass); Fiji; Hong Kong (China); Honolulu (Hawaii); Bangkok (Thailand); Cleveland (Ohio); Cleveland Metroparks Zoo; Home movies; Cat Cay (Bahamas); Photograph albums; Trans World Airlines; Lurline (Ship); Cleveland Zoological Park; Crawford, Frederick Coolidge
- Films, 1936-1980; 38 items
  Scope and Contents
  The Films series is arranged in seven roughly chronological subseries, and consists of 38 16mm films. The series has two primary areas of focus, with 12 of the films coming from trips Crawford took to his vacation home in Cat Cay, Bahamas, and 19 of the films produced from a safari Crawford, along with Gordon and Vernon Stouffer, sponsored in 1955, which resulted in the collection of a number of specimens for the Cleveland Zoo. Other Crawford travel represented in the collection includes trips to Europe in 1936 and 1939, a trip around the world in 1959, a cruise from Cleveland to Fiji in 1958, a trip to Russia in 1959, a trip to the Middle East and Greece in 1961, and trips to his other homes in Vermont and Massachusetts.
  - Europe, 1936, 1939; 1
    - Reversal, Original, 16mm, si., col., 1936-1939; 700 film feet (Freezer Smith Inspection Room, Reel RL10007-16mm-0016)
  - Cat Cay, Bahamas, 1941-1980; 2
    - Cat Cay '41, '42, '46, '47 & '48, 1941-1948; 1
      - Reversal, Original, 16mm, si., col., 1941-1948; 1200 film feet (Freezer Smith Inspection Room, Reel RL10007-16mm-0003)
    - Cat Cay Apr. 1948, Mako Shark, Return from Midway; 2. Dec '48-Jan '49; 3. Jan-Feb '49; 4. Cat Cay 1949; 5. Suzie & Girls, Anderson boat to Everts, Nassau, Miami, Hi at Cat Cay, 1948-1949; 2
      - Reversal, Original, 16mm, si., col., 1948-1949; 1500 film feet (Oversize-film-can 1, Reel RL10007-16mm-0004)
    - Cat Cay, 1950, 1951, 1952; Xmas '50 - Jan '51 Monkey, Wrights; Winter 51 - Monk - Bott; Winter 52 - Doc Beck etc., 4
      - Reversal, Original, 16mm, si., col., 1951-1952; 1000 film feet (Freezer Smith Inspection Room, Reel RL10007-16mm-0006)
    - Cat Cay (Kendrick), Dec '53-April '54, 1953 December - 1954 April; 6
      - Reversal, Original, 16mm, si., col., 1953 December - 1954 April; 1200 film feet (Box 3, Reel RL10007-16mm-0008)
    - Cat Cay 1953 Jan-May; Dec '54-Mar '55; Stouffers, 1953 December - 1955 March; 7
      - Reversal, Original, 16mm, si., col., 1953 December - 1955 March; 1500 film feet (Oversize-film-can 2, Reel RL10007-16mm-0009)
    - Cat Cay, 1957; Allen visit - a record of 2 weeks of Allen & Milburn visit only, 8
      - Reversal, Original, 16mm, si., col., 1957; 800 film feet (Box 4, Reel RL10007-16mm-0010)
    - Cat Cay, Nov '58 to Apr. '59; Colwell; Gwinn; Zeder; Stark; Allen; Stouffer; Kings; Gustin; French; Carpenter; Buttum; Hecket; Wasey anniversary; J.D. Wrights; Ft. Lauderdale to Cat Cay; Shaker Snow; Bert Lyons place; High Tide sign; Night Movies; Allens Clown, 1958 November - 1959 April; 9
      - Reversal, Original, 16mm, si., col., 1958 November - 1959 April; 1650 film feet (Oversize-film-can 3, Reel RL10007-16mm-0011)
    - Cat Cay, December '60 to March '61, 1960 December - 1961 March; 10
      - Reversal, Original, 16mm, si., col., 1960 December - 1961 March; 1300 film feet (Box 3, Reel RL10007-16mm-0012)
    - Cat Cay, Dec '61-Apr. '62, 1961 December - 1962 April; 11
      - Reversal, Original, 16mm, si., col., 1961 December - 1962 April; 1400 film feet (Oversize-film-can 4, Reel RL10007-16mm-0013)
    - Cat Cay, circa 1980; 12
      Film made by Industrial Media Association.
      - Composite, Original, 16mm, sd., col., circa 1980; 700 film feet (Box 3, Reel RL10007-16mm-0014)
  - Old farm, old home Crawford in Guildhall, VT, 1952-1956; 3
    - Reversal, Original, 16mm, si., col., 1952-1956; 900 film feet (Box 1, Reel RL10007-16mm-0020)
  - Around the world trip, 1955; 4
    - Rd World #1; 1955; Honolulu to Japan, 13
      - Reversal, Original, 16mm, si., col., 1955; 1100 film feet (Box 2, Reel RL10007-16mm-0001)
    - Rd World #2; 1955; Hong Kong to Bangkok to Ceylon, 14
      - Reversal, Original, 16mm, si., col., 1955; 1300 film feet (Box 2, Reel RL10007-16mm-0002)
  - Safari, 1955-1957; 5
    In 1955 Frederick Crawford, along with Gordon and Vernon Stouffer and representatives of the Cleveland Zoo, traveled to Kenya on safari, to collect specimens for the zoo. Along with the original silent reversal films in the Safari subseries, there are three composite films that have soundtracks and use footage from the safari, one of which, "Whose Zoo?", was a production created for the Cleveland Zoo.
    - Safari sound reel 1, 1957; 15
      Jambo Porini, the Cleveland Zoo East Africa Expedition, sponsored by Frederick C. Crawford and Gordon and Vernon Stouffer, incorporating the 1955 Crawford safari footage.
      - Composite, Original, 16mm, sd., col., 1957; 1500 film feet (Box 1, Reel RL10007-16mm-0022)
    - Safari sound reel 2, 1957; 16
      - Composite, Original, 16mm, sd., col., 1957; 1500 film feet (Box 1, Reel RL10007-16mm-0023)
    - Safari #1, 1955; 17
      - Reversal, Original, 16mm, si., col., 1955; 900 film feet (Box 1, Reel RL10007-16mm-0024)
    - Africa Duplicate, 1955; 18
      - Duplicate, Original, 16mm, si., col., 1955; 700 film feet (Box 1, Reel RL10007-16mm-0025)
    - Safari #2, 1955; 19
      - Reversal, Original, 16mm, si., col., 1955; 700 film feet (Box 4, Reel RL10007-16mm-0026)
    - Africa Duplicate, 1955; 20
      - Duplicate, Original, 16mm, si., col., 1955; 800 film feet (Box 3, Reel RL10007-16mm-0027)
    - Safari #3, 1955; 21
      - Reversal, Original, 16mm, si., col., 1955; 600 film feet (Box 4, Reel RL10007-16mm-0028)
    - Africa Duplicate 3, 1955; 22
      - Duplicate, Original, 16mm, si., col., 1955; 1000 film feet (Box 4, Reel RL10007-16mm-0029)
    - Safari #4, 1955; 23
      - Reversal, Original, 16mm, sd., col., 1955; 1200 film feet (Box 2, Reel RL10007-16mm-0030)
    - Africa Duplicate, 1955; 24
      - Duplicate, Original, 16mm, si., col., 1955; 800 film feet (Box 4, Reel RL10007-16mm-0031)
    - Safari #5, 1955; 25
      - Reversal, Original, 16mm, si., col., 1955; 750 film feet (Box 4, Reel RL10007-16mm-0032)
    - Africa Duplicate 5, 1955; 26
      - Duplicate, Original, 16mm, si., col., 1955; 900 film feet (Box 2, Reel RL10007-16mm-0033)
    - Safari #6, 1955; 27
      - Reversal, Original, 16mm, si., col., 1955; 700 film feet (Box 2, Reel RL10007-16mm-0034)
    - Africa Duplicate; #6 Dupe, 1955; 28
      - Duplicate, Original, 16mm, si., col., 1955; 1000 film feet (Box 2, Reel RL10007-16mm-0035)
    - Safari #7, 1955; 29
      - Reversal, Original, 16mm, si., col., 1955; 1300 film feet (Box 2, Reel RL10007-16mm-0036)
    - Safari #7, 1955; 30
      - Duplicate, Original, 16mm, si., col., 1955; 1300 film feet (Oversize-film-can 6, Reel RL10007-16mm-0037)
    - Safari B&H Extra #8, 1955; 31
      - Reversal, Original, 16mm, si., col., 1955; 700 film feet (Box 2, Reel RL10007-16mm-0038)
    - Africa Duplicate, 1955; 32
      - Duplicate, Original, 16mm, si., col., 1955; 800 film feet (Box 3, Reel RL10007-16mm-0039)
    - Whose Zoo? Safari '55, Fisher film, 1957; 33
      A film observing the 50th anniversary of the Cleveland Zoo, incorporating the 1955 Crawford safari footage.
      - Reversal, Original, 16mm, sd., col., 1957; 625 film feet (Box 4, Reel RL10007-16mm-0040)
  - Lurline Cruise, Cleveland to Fiji, 1958; 6
    - Reversal, Original, 16mm, si., col., 1958; 1300 film feet (Box 3, Reel RL10007-16mm-0015)
  - Russia, 1959 May-June; 7
    - Composite, Original, 16mm, si., col., 1959 May-June; 1400 film feet (Box 1, Reel RL10007-16mm-0021)
  - Holy Land, Greece, 1961 April 16-June 10; 8
    - Holy Land, Greece, Apr 16-June 10, 1961, #1; reel #26A, 1961 April 16-June 10; 34
      - Reversal, Original, 16mm, si., col., 1961 April 16-June 10; 1600 film feet (Oversize-film-can 5, Reel RL10007-16mm-0017)
    - Holyland-Greece, April 16-June10, 1961, #2, Jerusalem to Athens; end of Greece #2, Plato's olive (cut), view Bay of Salamis on drive west of Athens; reel #26B, 1961 April 16-June 10; 35
      - Reversal, Original, 16mm, si., col., 1961 April 16-June 10; 900 film feet (Box 1, Reel RL10007-16mm-0018)
  - Lake Trip, Cotuit, Massachusetts, 1964; 9
    - Reversal, Original, 16mm, si., col., 1964; 1100 film feet (Box 1, Reel RL10007-16mm-0019)
- Related Materials, 1953; 0.5 Linear Feet
  The Related Materials series consists of a photo album presented to Frederick Crawford by Trans World Airlines in 1953, documenting an around-the-world survey, in which Crawford participated as a technical consultant, that TWA completed in 1952.
  - Trans World Airlines, "Star of America," Around the world survey flight, November 11-December 14, 1952, 1953; 0.5 Linear Feet; 11.75 in. x 10 in. (Box 5)